today I'm going to talk about one of the
most important and discussed topic which
is demand forecasting demand forecasting
is very important especially for the
manufacturing organization so they need
to know what they're going to sell and
and buy what time period so when we talk
about demand forecasting we should look
into the three level of uh Horizons the
one is a long-term demand focusing so
when you Outsource something that means
you're relying on a supply lead time
therefore you have to give a forecast to
A supplier so they know what you have to
produce what would be your demand going
forward this video is brought to you by
us SC duo we provide awesome courses
guides best practices for supply chain
Community hi folks welcome to one more
episode of SM du knowledge today I'm
going to talk about one of the most
important and discuss topic which is
demand forecasting everyone wants to
talk about demand forecasting it has
been there since ages but we are going
to do deep dive today why demand
forecasting is important and what is
demand forecasting yeah so let's look
into the the very definition of demand
forecasting demand forecasting is the
Strategic process that helps
organizations make systematic estimation
about the probable demand for his
products in order to make structured
production plans accordingly in a
simplest term demand forecasting is an
estimate of future sales so with this
definition demand forecasting is very
important especially for the
manufacturing organization so they need
to know what they're going to sell and
and buy what time period you know they
have to grow into a certain market share
they have to grow in a certain markets
they have to basically grow in a certain
product line so an estimation is very
important it is important for any
business plan or for any shortterm and
long-term uh planning of the business so
when we talk about demand fusting we
should look into the three level of uh
Horizons the one is a long-term demand
focusing that is generally done for up
to 3 years in some businesses 5 years
but mostly up to 1 to 3 years where you
look into a division level forast a
product line level forecast a country
level forecast to set up your plans of
how much you want to grow or in certain
certain product line how you basically
want to exit the second is a mid-range
demand forecasting that means you talk
about basically 1 to 3 years which is
generally in the business is known as uh
midterm plan or for one year is called
budget and that means you set up a plan
that you want to grow 5% from uh
previous years you want to goow 10% from
the previous year or what you want to
grow uh buy or maybe in certain product
line as I said earlier you want to
basically exit or by certain brands you
want to exit because you're not making
money or it's not growing as as fast as
possible so mid-range plan is also
important most businesses is known as a
midterm planning or budgeting the third
one is more short-term planning that
means we talk about month two Monon
demand changes and the best process for
that is a sales and operation planning
process which I've discussed before the
benefit and why snop is important so
there's a link on above I've given so
you can watch this video but you can
also see my snop course which I've given
the link below where I have explained
what sop uh what are the five stage
processes what is the input and output
what are the best practices and most
importantly what are the most common
barriers and how can you use this course
to basically avoid those barriers and be
successful in your snop process so I've
also basically published uh ultimate
guide for the mon forecasting which you
can go and download from the guide
section there's a link below as well
where I talked about in detail demand
forecasting methods how to improve your
demand forecasting accuracy
what are the process you have to follow
and a lot more information you can get
from this the first and the most
important reason of the demand
forecasting is to improve customer
satisfaction because to have a good
customer satisfaction you basically you
need four things you know uh Supply
product on time at the good cost at the
good quality and also on a quickest lead
time so that means you have to have a
product available and if you're working
with your long lead term suppliers and
how you going to do this the only way to
do that is to focus it better that means
product is available so when the
customers order something it's available
on the Shelf to ship it literally as
simple as that the second is to reduce
the inventory stock up so in most of the
businesses you have almost outsourced
something right because you only focus
on your core processes or core
competencies so when you Outsource
something that means you're relying on a
supply lead time therefore you have to
give a for cost to a supplier so they
know what you have to produce what would
be your demand going forward so they can
plan their production their raw material
their people their machine capacity so
on so forth right so this demand forus
how them understand your demand so
therefore they can produce on time when
you place them a firm order and this is
especially very important when you work
with the longly term suppliers like
India China or or or or whoever even in
the case of just in time Supply when you
talk about automotive industry the
forecast is also play a big role I mean
if the the theory everybody thinks just
in time means you
every 6 hours but it it doesn't work
like that to apply to a a manufacturing
line of automotive every 6 hours or 4
hours or whatever the tech time is the
suppliers always need a for car so they
have enough product or enough buffer
available to keep feeding to the just in
time production line whatever that may
be is so demand forecasting is also help
in effective production scheduling so
I've written a Blog and also a made a
video on five levels of planning I mean
there's a link I have given
uh Below in comments box or you can see
up there as well so in this one I
explain how you take your uh basically
anal budget convert into your monthly
forecast into snop then convert into
master schedule your production plans so
once you know what you're going to
produce then you can uh have enough
people available enough machines
available enough ra material available
so you can use your resource effectively
a good demand forecast or let's call it
a more accurate demand forecast help you
reduce Safety stock so if you look into
any Safety stock formula it talks about
four variables right the one is demand
average demand the second is uh demand
variation uh lead time and lead time
variation so again I've written the blog
on the six formulas on the Safety stock
which you can see the link below but in
all formulas these four variables have
been used so if you are forecasting it
better that means you are increasing
your your chances of accurately
estimating your demand so therefore
you're reducing your demand variation so
that means you can be more confident in
reducing a buffer stock that means
you're basically saving some of your
working capital which you can use
somewhere else number five is a good
demand forecasting also helped you
reduce obsolescence cost I mean there's
also argument that you know lot of poor
forecasting have created lot of excess
obsolete inventory in the supply chain
and that is true right but in in this
this case we talking about a better more
accurate demand forecast how it can help
to reduce obsolesence cost in your
supply chain because what will happen is
you don't have to order big batches you
don't have to order inventory which is a
a basically you might need it or for
made to order business right so if you
have a good demand focusing process you
can be very sure you're going to order
based on the seasonality based on the
market changes product changes
promotions right and this what I'm
talking about how it will help to reduce
obsolescence in supply chain number six
demand forecasting is important because
it will help you manage your shipping
and distribution better and you might be
thinking I mean how what drives me
absolute Bonkers then you know we work
very hard to get all the right material
to have the right people to produce on
time and then we go to our shipping team
or distribution team say oh why you're
not shipping and they will say oh we got
we haven't got enough people it's it
never makes sense to me right I mean how
the distri people can say we we don't
know because the fact is they don't know
because we never really shared the any
Peak demount or any lower demount P to
them so they can understand how many
people they need I mean this is a big
bigger conversation just to make it
simple so I used to share uh uh let's
call it a monthly or a weekly forecast
with or number of units we have to ship
which we can convert into number of
lines and once we convert number of
lines so we know that to ship that many
lines or ship nodes how many people we
need based on the picking time we have
in the warehouse the the calculation is
slightly more complex but the point is
we need to know what volumes we are
shipping to understand how many people
we need right therefore a good demount
forecasting help you have the right
distribution planning for shipments also
for people you need how many containers
you need and most importantly how much
space you need let me give you one more
example so when in when I was in UK in
uh in the summer period when we know
that lot of people go on holiday that
means there's a manufacturing shutdown
so what you do because you still have to
supply the product in August and July
right so we have to do some stock build
because we have to stock build that mean
we need more space right so that actual
customer demand is is in the later in
the month but we have to do the stock
build in the month of May and June for
example for that reason we have to
forast how many unit we need how much
space we need therefore we can do some
calculation in terms of a space capacity
of the warehouse as well so therefore
for shipping and Logistics demand for
cusing is important number seven is the
impact of the pricing and promotion of
the demand forecasting right so if you
if we know that that increase the price
generally what will happen your
Distributors order earlier because they
want to basically take an advantage
before the price hike similarly if
you're rting promotion that we need to
have some level of buffer inventory
extend inventory available in either
case pricing increases or price changes
or the promotions at the distributor
level need to be forecasted and need to
be passed on to your suppliers in your
manufacturing so they can have enough
capacity available people available raw
material available so they can make sure
that if there's any price changes needs
to happen or promotion needs to happen
the material is available to ship online
number eight a good demand forecasting
help you negotiate with your supplier
better what I mean by that so what will
happen is that if you are giving a good
demand for cost to your supplier that
means they know that there's a certain
level of volumes you are going to order
and therefore it gives you a leverage to
negotiate earlier a better price if you
don't give forecast that means you may
maybe have a less power of negotiation
and it also builds your credibility as a
customer so your suppliers know that you
are a credible customer you have a
continuous volume there's a long-term
business and they show more Affinity you
know better relationship to work with
you and help you out when you really
need to a good demand fusing process
helps your product management team and
your sales team to plan their strategies
better as well so if they want to launch
a new product or they want to launch a
new variation of the product that means
they know what basically stock build
they need how they need to do phase in
and phase out right so it will help you
your product team and your sales team to
perform their jobs or Implement their
sales strategies and the product
Amendment strategies so when it come to
the demand forecasting method you know
for fun I posted on the LinkedIn and
Twitter which quite quite viral in fact
which is U demand focusing is almost
like making love everybody wants to be
good at it but nobody knows what's the
best technique look into the blog I've
written in terms of the importance of
demand forecasting there's a link below
and also the guide as well so with
putting this all together I'm sure you
will find a better way of demand
forecasting so therefore you can take
the advantage of the all the nine
factors I have mentioned in terms of the
importance of demand forecasting right
so again as usual thank you for watching
if you was last that long keep it simple
and keep it real ciao
[Music]